<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<node name="/" xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <interface name="org.freedesktop.NetworkManager.Device.WiMax">
    <method name="GetNspList">
      <annotation name="org.freedesktop.DBus.GLib.CSymbol" value="impl_device_get_nsp_list"/>
      <arg name="nsps" type="ao" direction="out">
        <tp:docstring>
          List of NSP object paths
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Get the list of NSPs visible to this device.
      </tp:docstring>
    </method>

    <property name="Nsps" type="ao" access="read">
      <tp:docstring>
        List of object paths of Network Service Providers (NSPs) visible to this
        WiMAX device.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="HwAddress" type="s" access="read">
      <tp:docstring>
        Hardware address of the device.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="CenterFrequency" type="u" access="read">
      <tp:docstring>
        Center frequency (in KHz) of the radio channel the device is using to
        communicate with the network when connected.  Has no meaning when the
        device is not connected.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="Rssi" type="i" access="read">
      <tp:docstring>
        RSSI of the current radio link in dBm.  This value indicates how strong
        the raw received RF signal from the base station is, but does not
        indicate the overall quality of the radio link.  Has no meaning when the
        device is not connected.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="Cinr" type="i" access="read">
      <tp:docstring>
        CINR (Carrier to Interference + Noise Ratio) of the current radio link
        in dB.  CINR is a more accurate measure of radio link quality.  Has no
        meaning when the device is not connected.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="TxPower" type="i" access="read">
      <tp:docstring>
        Average power of the last burst transmitted by the device, in units of
        0.5 dBm.  i.e. a TxPower of -11 represents an actual device TX power of
        -5.5 dBm.  Has no meaning when the device is not connected.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="Bsid" type="s" access="read">
      <tp:docstring>
        The ID of the serving base station as received from the network.  Has
        no meaning when the device is not connected.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="ActiveNsp" type="o" access="read">
      <tp:docstring>
        Object path of the NSP currently used by the WiMax device.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <signal name="PropertiesChanged">
        <arg name="properties" type="a{sv}" tp:type="String_Variant_Map">
            <tp:docstring>
                A dictionary mapping property names to variant boxed values.
            </tp:docstring>
        </arg>
        <tp:docstring>
            Emitted when the WiMax device's properties changed.
        </tp:docstring>
    </signal>

    <signal name="NspAdded">
        <arg name="nsp" type="o">
            <tp:docstring>
                The object path of the newly found NSP.
            </tp:docstring>
        </arg>
        <tp:docstring>
            Emitted when a new NSP is found by the device.
        </tp:docstring>
    </signal>

    <signal name="NspRemoved">
      <arg name="nsp" type="o">
            <tp:docstring>
                The object path of the NSP that has disappeared.
            </tp:docstring>
        </arg>
        <tp:docstring>
            Emitted when an NSP disappears from view of the device.
        </tp:docstring>
    </signal>

  </interface>
</node>
